<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Cavaliers catechisme: or, The reformed Protestant catechising the antichristian papists, malignants, incendiaries, and other ill-affected persons under the name of cavaliers. With their distinct answer thereunto.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78398</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1567</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E100_22</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11848</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859153</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859153</idno>
            <idno type="VID">155869</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78398)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 155869)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 18:E100[22])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Cavaliers catechisme: or, The reformed Protestant catechising the antichristian papists, malignants, incendiaries, and other ill-affected persons under the name of cavaliers. With their distinct answer thereunto.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Watson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A satire.</note>
                  <note>A different work than Wing C1568: The cavaliers catechisme, and confession of his faith.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May. 3.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Royalists --  England --  History --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Humor --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:155869:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:155869:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CAVALIERS Catechiſme: OR, The Reformed Proteſtant catechiſing the Antichriſtian Papiſts, Malignants, Incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diaries, and other ill-affected Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons under the name of <hi>Cavaliers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WITH <hi>Their diſtinct Anſwer thereunto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Watſon.</hi> 1643.<add>May .3.</add>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:155869:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:155869:2"/>
            <head>The Cavaliers Catechiſme.</head>
            <p>
               <label>Queſtion.</label>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat is your name?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Cavalier.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Qu.</label> Who gave you that name?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> My ſeducers and deceivers, in my innocency, wherein I was made a member of the Church of Rome, and conſequently a limb of Antichriſt, an enemy to all goodneſſe, the child of the divell, an inheriter of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of darkneſſe, amongſt the infernall ſpirits that rule in the ayre of this terreſtriall globe.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Qu.</label> How were your Witneſſes denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Lack-wit and Ignorance: for if they had wit and knowledge, they would not have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the title of a Gentleman to a clowne or Corydon.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Qu.</label> What did your Witneſſes promiſe you ſhould perform when you came to maturity and ripe age, when you received your name?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:155869:3"/>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> That I ſhould forſake all Piety and godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, all vertue and purity, the true and Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Religion, grounded upon the verity of Gods word, that I ſhould perſecute all profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of the ſame, envy all goodneſſe and good men, promote the Romiſh Religion and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Antichriſt, by any manner of meanes whatſoever, be it by treaſonable plots againſt Princes or States, or by rayſing publike Warre and ſedition in Common-Wealths, and the like.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Qu.</label> Art thou able to doe theſe things of thy ſelfe, that were promiſed for the?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> No verily, but by the helpe of the reſt of my fellow members received into that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, I doubt not to be inabled and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened to performe all that was promiſed on behalfe.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Qu.</label> What is meant by your name Cavalier?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Knighthood, very unfit for me, for as I am told, it was a name firſt given to Gentlemen as an augmentation of honour, by the French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in the Warres, the word being derived of the French word Chivall, a Horſe, by which Troopers or Horſemen in battaile were called Chevaliers, by corruption of ſpeech in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe
<pb facs="tcp:155869:3"/>of time, called by the Engliſh Cavaliers, now Cavallers, or Cavaleers, but by the better ſort Cavaliers, by all which theſe particulars, may be collected, that as the world is now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated from the true pronunciation of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall word, ſo the naturall diſpoſition of men are degenerated to the word now in uſe, Caval<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, or Cavaliers, for in our actions there is no ſolidity, nor in our ſpeeches ſobriety, nor in our hearts integrity, but all our arguments are main<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tained by cavelling, and our actions defended by beſtiallity, and rude diſorderly behaviour, like unto untamed horſes, from whence we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the firſt denomination, whoſe order is altogether to diſorder and confound the warlike Rancks in Battaile, and to bring to confuſion and deſtruction, is the onely ſence they have of their preſent actions.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Qu.</label> Doe you conceive that the way you have been trained up and educated in from the time of your birth to this preſent, is to be defended by thoſe meanes as you have bin taught?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Yis truely, for theſe reaſons,
<list>
                  <item>1. In reſpect of the Commandements I have received from the Church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wherein I was received a member.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:155869:4"/>
                  <item> 2 In reſpect of the danger I am told I ſhall fall into, and puniſhment I am worthy of, if I deſert the ſervice of that cauſe to which I have been devoted, and which my Witneſſes inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged themſelves for me in my infancy, that I ſhould uphold and maintain when I ſhould come to age?</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Qu.</label> What are the commandements you have learned, and that you conceive your ſelfe bound to obſerve and keep?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Theſe following.
<list>
                  <item>1 That I ſhould obſerve the will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of his Holineſſe of Rome in all matters touching ſalvation, without the uſe of the Scriptures, they being by him counted defici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and have not ſufficient inſtructions contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in them to lead a pious life, and bring to fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture happineſſe.</item>
                  <item>2 To commit treaſon againſt Kings that op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe his Holineſſe, and reject his doctrinall tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions.</item>
                  <item>3 To commit fornication, adultery, rapine, and the like.</item>
                  <item>4 To reject the Chriſtian Sabbath, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre the Jewiſh.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:155869:4"/>
                  <item> 5. To admit of no leſſe then ſeven Sacraments neceſſary to ſalvation.</item>
                  <item>6. To ſweare, and forſweare, for the defence of the Catholique cauſe.</item>
                  <item>7. To cozen, deceive, and circumvent, our Neighbours for our own advantage.</item>
                  <item>8. To acknowledge no god greater, or more to be reverenced, and worſhiped, then the Pope of Rome.</item>
                  <item>9. To worſhip and adore Images, as much as Chriſt himſelfe.</item>
                  <item>10. To beare falſe witneſſe againſt our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, for any occaſion whatſoever.</item>
                  <item>11. For all which the Popes indulgent pardon is ſufficient to preſerve from damnation.</item>
                  <item>12. That there is no greater damnation, then the Popes curſe, and excomumcation.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Qu.</label> Doe you believe all theſe precepts?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Yis, and have and will to the loſſe of my life and fortunes, (if I had any) obſerve and keep them.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Qu.</label> What is a Sacrament according to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of your Church?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> It is a ſigne of a thing ſignified, which we cannot diſcern with the Eye, but by the ſigne.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:155869:5"/>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Explain the ſame, according to your ſence and knowledge?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Then thus, by the ſigne of the Croſſe is ſignified the cuncifying of ☞, by the picture of the Virgin Mary, we are taught that ſhe was the Mother of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> and queen of heaven, by the picture of the Apoſtles, we are taught to remember that they were the founders of the Church, &amp; of that ſanctity &amp; power, that they are now in heavan able to cure the diſeaſes of living Saints on earth, as they did when they were on Earth, and therefore we are us much bound to pray to them for helpe upon any ocaſion, as to God, they knowing our wants, by a fellow feeling of our miferies when they lived with us, many other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples I could give, by which you may underſtand what we mean by Sacraments,</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Then every Image or Picture, whether of Saints departed, Patriarkes, Prophets, or Apoſtles, are Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and to be ſacredly obſerved and kept?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Yis verrily, and as much in eſteem as the two Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments of Baptiſme and the Supper.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Q.</label> Are theſe the things you now take up Arms for, againſt your Country, and ſeeke to bring the ſame to ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter confuſion and deſtruction?</p>
            <p>
               <label>A.</label> Yis, and will never give over ſo long as life laſteth till we have reſtored the uſe of theſe things in the Church of England, or looſe our bodies in the enterprize, for our ſoules we have aſſured hope to have them ſaved after we have felt ſome ſmall time of puniſhment in Purgatory, and his Holineſſe, our chiefeſt hope and defence, come to heaven before us as a great Saint, and by his mediation and interceſſion, redeem us from that place of pain.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
